MARIA VICTORIA DIVELY

1070 Dogwood Lane Roaring Spring, Pennsylvania, 16673 (814) 569-1925 | Primary bdively@atlanticbb.net

OBJECTIVE:

I am a native, Spanish speaking Bilingual Teacher from Bogota, Colombia and a USA citizen of 17 years, with 8 years of teaching experience, with five of those years teaching Spanish at all grade levels, is seeking full time employment as a Spanish teacher in a school district that maintains high educational standards, who appreciates the Spanish language, and provides their students with opportunities for personal growth. I am confident that my strong organizational skills, thorough educational background, and ability to work well and communicate effectively with children of all ages, parents, colleagues, and supervisors would be a valuable addition for your school district.

SKILLS:

- •Bilingual speaker in education, business and communities at large. Skills to proficiently read, write and communicate in English and Spanish
- •Strong communication skills and a devotion to diversity
- •Methodical, patient and devoted to subjects that enhance the students' cultural understanding of Spanish-speaking countries, making positive connections between local communities in U.S. regions and those of Spanish-speaking countries, introducing them to new cultures and developing bilingual communication skills that are in demand
- •Prepared to teach Spanish grammar rules, spelling and diction, word pronunciation, sentence structure, punctuation, reading, and essay writing
- •Spanish teacher with outstanding bilingual vocabularies, with a firm grasp of correct word pronunciation and spelling and the ability to effortlessly break words down phonetically. Spanish teacher who is sensitive to the needs of a diverse range of students with bilingual speaking skills
- •Comfortable explaining differences in gender nouns, subject/verb agreement, and use of accent symbols
- •Able to teach critical thinking while advancing students' bilingual verbal and written communication skills

- •Experience and knowledge about teaching effectively to suit various learning styles
- •Relaxed speaking in front of large groups in English and Spanish
- •Able to inspire students to converse in Spanish
- •Experience in working with both students and parents
- •Grounded in grade-level expectations and progress indicators to keep students working toward fluency
- •Translator/Interpreter in local hospitals
- Technology knowledge
- •Translated 36 brochures into Spanish for Camtran (Cambria County Transit Authority) of Johnstown, PA
- •Basic intermediate language French, Italian and Portuguese

TEACHING EXPERIENCE:

SPANISH TEACHER • TUSSEY MOUNTAIN HIGH SCHOOL SAXTON, PA

JAN 2016 – JUNE 2,2017

- •Beginners (8th Grade), I (9th Grade), II (10th Grade), III (11th Grade) & IV (12th Grade)
- •Teach Spanish language and cultural classes to a diverse array of students of varying ages and abilities
- •Plan and organize hands-on activities that encourage active student participation, involvement, and team work
- •Assigned and graded class work and homework
- •Plan and prepare lesson plans, organize for instruction and implement testing
- •Prepare semester ending report cards
- •Implemented a variety of teaching tools to accommodate all learning styles
- •Monitor and evaluate student progress and potential
- •Classroom management and organization
- •Maintain an orderly, peaceful, and positive learning environment, applying disciplinary measures when necessary

- •Incorporating cultural and historical components into the curriculum to diversify and expand learning material
- •Fostered a positive and safe learning atmosphere
- •Adviser for Spanish Club
- •Adult monitor for Bible study class

SPANISH I TEACHER • ALTOONA AREA JUNIOR HIGH SCHOOL ALTOONA, PA

NOV 2015 – JAN 2016

- •Devised & implemented the required weekly lesson plans and testing
- •Planned and conducted activities for a balanced program of instruction, demonstration and work time that provided students with opportunities to observe, question and investigate
- •Assigned and graded class work and homework
- •Prepared reports on students and activities
- •Performed other duties such as assisting in school libraries, hall and cafeteria monitoring

SPANISH TEACHER • BISHOP GUILFOYLE CATHOLIC HIGH SCHOOL ALTOONA, PA

AUG 2012 – SEPT 2015

- •Devised and implemented the required weekly lesson plan and implemented testing
- •Assigned and graded class work and homework
- •Planned and conducted activities for a balanced program of demonstration and work time that provided students with opportunities to observe, question and investigate
- •Prepared students for later grades by encouraging them to explore learning opportunities and to preserve with challenging tasks
- •Prepared objectives and outlines for coursed of study, following curriculum guidelines or requirements of states and schools
- •Met with parents and guardians to discuss their children's progress and determine properties for their children and their resource needs
- •Conferred with other staff members to plan and schedule lessons promoting learning, following approved curricula and prepare reports on students and activities
- •Attended professional meetings, educational conferences and teacher training workshops to maintain and improve professional competence

- •Administered standardized ability and achievement tests and interpret results to determine students' strengths and areas of need
- •Performed administrative duties such as assisting in school libraries, hall and cafeteria monitoring
- •Fostered a positive and safe learning atmosphere
- •Prepared semester ending report cards
- •Adviser for Spanish Club

SUBSTITUTE TEACHER • ALTOONA AND BEDFORD AREAS SCHOOL DISTRICTS AND IU8
BLAIR AND BEDFORD COUNTIES, PA

- AUG 2009 JUN 2012
- •Adapted quickly and enforced rules for behavior and procedures for maintaining order among the students
- •Adapted teaching methods and instructional materials to meet students' varying needs and interests
- •Followed teachers plans or prepared own materials for class activities
- •Performed administrative duties such as assisting in school libraries, hall and cafeteria monitoring

THERAPEUTIC SUPPORT SPECIALIST • CHILDREN'S BEHAVIORAL HEALTH INC.

JOHNSTOWN, PA

AUG 2011 – MAY 2012

- •Established and enforced good behaviors in the classrooms
- •Instructed special skills to work with autistic children

OTHER WORK EXPERIENCE:

TRANSLATOR SPANISH – ENGLISH – SPANISH ● FROSTY HOLLOW FARMS ROARING SPRING, PA MAR 2000 – AUG 2012

ACCOUNT EXECUTIVE ● FEDERAL EXPRESS CORPORATION, BOGOTÁ, COLOMBIA JAN 1995 – NOV 1999

EDUCATION:

BACHELOR of SCIENCE DEGREE in SECONDARY EDUCATION ● SAINT FRANCIS UNIVERSITY, LORETTO, PA

- •Credits Earned:51 with GPA of 3.389 Bachelor of Science Degree in Secondary Education 7-12 with a concentration in Spanish
- •MAJOR: Secondary Education 7-12 with a concentration in Spanish
- •MINOR: Education Certification in the teaching of Spanish by April 26 2017 from the Pennsylvania Department of Education
- •Successfully passed the Spanish World Language PA Praxis Test with score of 181
- •4 Classes short of obtaining my Master's Degree of Education

BACHELOR'S DEGREE ● EXTERNADO DE COLOMBIA UNIVERSITY, BOGOTÁ, SOUTH AMERICA

•MAJOR: Business Administration

PERSONAL:

- •Married to a school bus driver and mother of 3,aged 16,14 and 12 years of age.All are bilingual
- •Enjoy spending time with the family, attending church and going to the gym